<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://lognitilab.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://lognitilab.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-06-17T17:44:05+00:00</updated><id>https://lognitilab.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">LogNiti Lab</title><subtitle>Lab Profile </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Monitoring Daily Air Quality</title><link href="https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2024/airquality/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Monitoring Daily Air Quality"/><published>2024-05-15T13:28:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-15T13:28:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2024/airquality</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2024/airquality/"><![CDATA[<p>Air Quality is a crucial tool to communicate the quality of air in a given area, indicating the level of pollution and its potential impact on public health. It is calculated based on the concentrations of eight prominent pollutants, namely, Particulate Matter (PM<sub>10</sub> and PM<sub>2.5</sub>), Nitrogen Dioxide (NO<sub>2</sub>), Sulfur Dioxide (SO<sub>2</sub>), Carbon Monoxide (CO), Ozone (O<sub>3</sub>), Ammonia (NH<sub>3</sub>), and Lead (Pb). The estimation procedure involves continuous monitoring of these pollutants using a network of air quality monitoring stations across the country. Each pollutant’s concentration is measured and then converted into a normalized index value using standard formulas and breakpoint tables provided by the Central Pollution Control Board (CPCB). The highest index value among the pollutants determines the overall AQI for that location. This value is then categorized into six levels—ranging from ‘Good’ to ‘Severe’—to convey the health implications effectively to the public, aiding in the adoption of necessary precautio nary measures and policy decisions aimed at improving air quality.</p> <div class="l-page"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/index.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="455" width="800"></iframe> </div> <p><strong>Figure.</strong> Air quality index across different cities in India</p> <p>The Air Quality Index (AQI) is given by:</p> <p>\begin{equation} \label{eq:aqi} \text{AQI} = \max(\text{AQI}_ \text{PM2.5}, \text{AQI}_ \text{PM10}, \text{AQI}_ \text{NO2}, \text{AQI}_ \text{SO2}, \text{AQI}_ \text{O3}, \text{AQI}_ \text{NH3}) \end{equation}</p> <p>\begin{equation} \label{eq:aqip} \text{AQI}_ \text{p} = \frac{(\text{I}_ \text{high} - \text{I}_ \text{low})}{(\text{C}_ \text{high} - \text{C}_ \text{low})} \times (\text{C}_ \text{p} - \text{C}_ \text{low}) + \text{I}_ \text{low} \end{equation}</p> <p>where:</p> <ul> <li>\(\text{AQI}_ \text{p}\) is the AQI for pollutant \(p\).</li> <li>\(\text{C}_ \text{p}\) is the concentration of pollutant \(p\).</li> <li>\(\text{C}_ \text{high}\) and \(\text{C}_ \text{low}\) are the concentration breakpoints that bracket \(\text{C}_ \text{p}\).</li> <li>\(\text{I}_ \text{high}\) and \(\text{I}_ \text{low}\) are the AQI breakpoints corresponding to \(\text{C}_ \text{high}\) and \(\text{C}_ \text{low}\).</li> </ul> <div class="l-page"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/level.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="605" width="450"></iframe> </div> <p><strong>Figure.</strong> Air quality level across different cities in India</p> <p><strong>Table.</strong> Air quality index and level and associated pollutant concenrtation range</p> <table id="table" data-toggle="table" data-url="/assets/json/airquality.json"> <thead> <tr> <th data-field="AQI Category">AQI Category</th> <th data-field="AQI">AQI</th> <th data-field="PM10">PM<sub>10</sub></th> <th data-field="PM2.5">PM<sub>2.5</sub></th> <th data-field="NO2">NO<sub>2</sub></th> <th data-field="O3">O<sub>3</sub></th> <th data-field="CO">CO</th> <th data-field="SO2">SO<sub>2</sub></th> <th data-field="NH3">NH<sub>3</sub></th> <th data-field="Pb">Pb</th> </tr> </thead> </table> <p><sup>CO in mg/m<sup>3</sup> and other pollutants in μg/m<sup>3</sup>; 24-hourly average values for PM<sub>10</sub>, PM<sub>2.5</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>,SO<sub>2</sub>, NH<sub>3</sub>, and Pb, and 8-hourly values for CO and O<sub>3</sub>.</sup></p> <div class="l-page"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/pollutant.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="605" width="450"></iframe> </div> <p><strong>Figure.</strong> Prominent pollutant across different cities in India</p>]]></content><author><name>Anmol Pahwa</name></author><category term="miscellaneous"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Monitor daily air quality updates to index, level, and prominent pollutant across different cities in India, sourced from the daily bulletin report of Central Pollution Control Board, Government of India.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Towards last-mile delivery with electric vehicles</title><link href="https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2022/electricvehicles/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Towards last-mile delivery with electric vehicles"/><published>2022-10-16T17:32:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-16T17:32:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2022/electricvehicles</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2022/electricvehicles/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Is last-mile delivery with electric vehicles viable given the stochastic and dynamic nature of the delivery environments?</strong></p> <p>Freight transportation is the backbone of the economy, moving goods between various production, consumption, and disposal sites. The rise of e-commerce platforms and with it the ability to shop on-the-fly (on-demand economy) has substantially increased this flow of goods in the urban environments. Conceptually, this increased flow brings prosperity for the consumer and the retailer, thereby fostering economic growth – 1st pillar of sustainability, and expands access to essential products for otherwise disadvantaged communities, thus improving social equity – 3rd pillar of sustainability. Further, since the retailer can consolidate deliveries and optimize delivery tours, e-commerce can significantly reduce shopping-travel-related emissions and can therefore render environmentally efficient flow of goods – 2nd pillar of sustainability. However, the competitive nature of e-commerce has prompted retailers to offer incentives to customers in the form of free shipping, faster delivery, and free returns, among others, which has resulted in inefficient flow of goods with substantial increase in shopping-travel-related emissions. These emissions, such as the greenhouse gases (CO<sub>2</sub>, CH<sub>4</sub>, etc.) adversely affect the health of the planet, while the criteria pollutants (NO<sub>x</sub>, PM, etc.) have negative impacts on human health. In 2017, the transportation sector in the US produced 1787 million metric tons of CO<sub>2</sub> emissions, thus contributing to more than a third of nation-wide CO<sub>2</sub> emissions. More than a quarter of these transportation-related CO<sub>2</sub> emissions were produced by freight vehicles alone, despite the freight sector accounting for less than a tenth of vehicular traffic. Considering the urgent need to address global climate change and the negative health impacts of criteria pollutants, it is pertinent that stakeholders (regulator and retailer) better plan and manage urban freight to foster a sustainable flow of goods that is economically viable, environmentally efficient, and socially equitable. To this end, using alternate fuel vehicles such as battery electric freight vehicles can render low-cost, zero-emission (tailpipe), equitable delivery of goods, though an effective utilization of these alternative delivery options is contingent upon stakeholders making appropriate decisions.</p> <p><strong>Regulator:</strong></p> <p><em>Incentivizing transition towards an electric delivery fleet</em></p> <p>A retailer’s choice to purchase a fleet of electric vehicles (trucks or delivery vans) depends on the total cost of ownership (TCO) of this technology against other options (e.g., diesel trucks). While an electric truck typically has a higher purchase cost in comparison to an equivalent diesel truck, the lower operational costs (maintenance and fuel cost) can justify the purchase of an electric truck fleet in the long-run. Nonetheless, the high upfront purchase cost of an electric truck with the potential operational cost savings far in the future, dissuades retailers to replace its diesel truck fleet with an electric truck fleet. Thus, considering these trade-offs for the retailer, government support in the form of incentives play a critical role in fostering the transition to zero emission vehicles. These incentives can be one-time purchase incentives such as the one offered under the Hybrid and Zero-Emission Trucks and Bus Voucher Incentive Program (HVIP) program in California, or continuous support incentives such as the one offered under the California Low Carbon Fuel Standard (LCFS) program wherein credits are disbursed based on the quantity of diesel fuel substituted and relative carbon intensity of the alternate fuel. Further, in California, these incentive programs are bolstered by the Advanced Clean Truck (ACT) rule which sets targets for truck manufacturers on minimum sales of alternate fuel trucks, thereby ensuring availability of a wide-range of industry competent electric trucks for retailers to purchase. Such supply- and demand- side incentives are essential to make electric trucks compete with diesel trucks until the electric powertrain and the associated battery technology achieve cost parity with diesel trucks.</p> <div class="row mt-3" style="text-align: center"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/15.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="50%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p style="font-size:0.7em; text-align: center">Typical truck-use by vocation (Vehicle Miles Traveled)</p> <p><em>Developing infrastructure to support last-mile electrification</em></p> <p>In addition to purchase and operational cost targeted incentives, government and other agencies support through public charging infrastructure has a critical role in influencing retailer’s purchase decision. Though electric trucks available in the market today have sufficient range to carry out typical day-to-day last-mile operations without having to be re-charged during the working hours as is evident from the figure above, range anxiety and consequently perceived lack of reliability in an extremely time-sensitive market can also dissuade the retailer to purchase electric vehicles. In fact, a sophisticated network of (fast) charging infrastructure is necessary to tackle the challenges in transitioning from a conventional diesel truck fleet in the short- and medium- term, wherein certain strategic aspects of the supply-chain cannot be re-configured. One such aspect is logistics network configuration. i.e., location of warehouses, fulfillment centers, consolidation facilities, delivery stations, vehicle depots, etc. Further, such facilities are constrained by land-use and warehousing patterns, and therefore may have to locate away from market. Thus, in certain markets, limited vehicle range can become serious hindrance to successful adaption of electric vehicles in the delivery fleet. In such markets, it becomes even more pertinent to provide incentives and establish a sophisticated network of fast-charging stations to encourage retailers to transition from conventional diesel-powered fleet to electric delivery vehicles. In addition, support for retrofits and other infrastructure upgrades at retailers’ vehicle depots may also be required.</p> <p><strong>Retailer:</strong></p> <p><em>Identifying best use case for electric delivery vehicles</em></p> <p>A retailer’s choice to deploy a fleet of electric trucks is contingent upon the delivery environment. In general, last-mile operations with conventional-sized class-5 delivery trucks (diesel or electric) is a good fit for markets with lenient temporal constraints that allow for demand consolidation and route optimization, and thus render low-cost delivery. However, as temporal constraints become stringent, consolidation levels drop leading to frequent less-than-truckload delivery tours, increased vehicle miles traveled, and therefore increased costs for the retailer. Nonetheless, due to a much lower operational cost of an electric truck in comparison to a diesel truck, the increase in costs for the retailer from stricter time-windows is less severe when operating an electric truck fleet instead. Thus, class-5 electric trucks can provide an 8% savings in comparison to the class-5 diesel truck for last-mile operations under 2-hr delivery time-window. In fact, for delivery under such strict time-windows, smaller electric vehicles or electric vans render up to 50% savings in comparison to conventional-sized class 5 diesel truck. Moreover, with improvements in the battery technology in the form of improved energy density, and faster charging rates, the delivery cost can be further reduced by as much as 25%, making electric delivery vehicles significantly better than diesel-powered delivery vehicles across all delivery environments (see figure below). These results highlight the potential opportunities with electric trucks to render low-cost, zero-emission, equitable delivery of goods.</p> <div class="row mt-3" style="text-align: center"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/16.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="50%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p style="font-size:0.7em; text-align: center">D2D – diesel/electric: Door-to-Door delivery with diesel/electric trucks</p> <p style="font-size:0.7em; text-align: center">Impact of battery characteristics on last-mile delivery costs with electric trucks under short time-windows</p> <p><em>Deploying and managing electric vehicles</em></p> <p>A retailer’s choice to operate a fleet of electric trucks depends on the reliability and consistency with which the retailer can carry out day-to-day last-mile operations in a dynamic, stochastic, and time-constrained environment, typical of e-commerce delivery in urban markets. The dynamic elements pertain to weather-related events, traffic accidents, vehicle failure, same-day customer requests, etc., while the stochastic elements pertain to travel speed, travel time, customer demand, and customer availability, among others. Such dynamic and stochastic changes in the environment can affect the capability of electric vehicles, especially smaller electric vans with limited battery size and vehicle range, to successfully carry out last-mile operations, unlike diesel vehicles. While a sophisticated network of fast-charging stations in such delivery markets can safeguard against operational failures, eco-routing and eco-driving strategies can further help the retailer extract the full potential of electric vehicles to effectively utilize battery energy and maximize vehicle range, and therefore ensure reliable last-mile operations. Such eco-routing strategies pertain to optimal path choice, while eco-driving strategies pertain to optimal vehicle operation – acceleration, cruising, braking, and idling. Typically, battery efficiency peaks at moderate level of vehicle operation, thus, passiveness or aggression behind the wheel renders a drop in battery efficiency, thereby increasing vehicle energy consumption. Thus, while eco-routing strategies guides vehicle towards energy-efficient route, eco-driving strategies guide vehicle to optimal battery use. Combined, these eco-routing and eco-driving strategies can help the retailer optimize its fleet use and therefore improve reliability of last-mile operations with electric fleet. In addition, optimizing fleet use through such strategies can potentially further reduce operational cost with minimal increase in total distance traveled and time taken to deliver goods. Further, owing to reduced heavy acceleration and braking events, these eco-driving strategies can lessen driver fatigue and therefore reduce traffic accidents, especially for retailers providing expedited service.</p> <p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p> <p>Last-mile delivery service in dense urban environments with lenient temporal constraints provides best opportunity to deploy electric delivery vehicles. In fact, across all market segments and delivery environments, electric trucks have proven to be competitive with diesel trucks, yet, despite such opportunities, challenges in transitioning from conventional diesel vehicle fleet to electric vehicle fleet remain. These challenges largely pertain to lack of reliability in dynamic and stochastic delivery environments. Due to such challenges, adoption of electric vehicles in the freight sector has been slow, while there is an urgent need to address global climate change and local criteria pollutant issues which have serious implications for the planet and human health, respectively. Nonetheless, with a joint effort between stakeholders (regulator and retailers), freight related externalities from last-mile delivery can be addressed. To begin with, upfront government support in the form of purchase incentives and/or continuous support with operational incentives can encourage the retailers to switch to electric vehicles for last-mile delivery. Such policy measures could mandate retailers to implement regular eco-driving training and assessment for its staff, not limited to only drivers but also managers, and therefore instill eco-friendly behavior top-down in its firm, as a prerequisite to subsidies, permits, licenses, etc. In addition, local governments must establish sufficient public charging infrastructure with fast charging capabilities in urban environments, near residential and commercial spaces. Thus, with stakeholders making such appropriate strategic, tactical, and operational choices, electric vehicles can be deployed for a low-cost, zero-emission, and equitable last-mile delivery.</p>]]></content><author><name>Anmol Pahwa</name></author><category term="moving-goods"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Is last-mile delivery with electric vehicles viable given the stochastic and dynamic nature of the delivery environments?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Eco-routing trucks to reduce externalities</title><link href="https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2022/ecorouting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Eco-routing trucks to reduce externalities"/><published>2022-08-04T17:32:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-04T17:32:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2022/ecorouting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2022/ecorouting/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Freight transportation is fundamental to economic growth, nonetheless, the trucks that haul this freight are pollution intensive, emitting greenhouse gases that affect the health of our planet, and criteria pollutants that adversely affect human health, and are also one of the leading cause for urban congestion and accidents. Can eco-routing trucks reduce freight related externalities? In this blog, we explore the opportunities and challenges in freight eco-routing.</strong></p> <p>In the past century, global climate change has become a pressing concern for the subsistence of humankind on earth. Swedish scientist, Svante Arrhenius, was the first to establish an anthropological link to the rise in global temperatures in 1896. Ever since then, rigorous scientific evidence has been collected, corroborating the greenhouse gas effect. Transportation is one of the major sectors that contributes to this effect, amounting to a share of 24% global carbon-dioxide emissions. Freight movement, which is typically characterized by high-intensity long-duration travel, renders a major chunk of these transportation-related emissions. Beyond freight’s impact on global climate change, criteria pollutants from urban freight movement adversely affect the health of local communities. The recent trends in freight distribution – the growth of e-commerce and subsequent increase in time sensitivity of demand – have significantly affected urban freight flows, resulting in frequent less-than-truckload urban freight movements on faster routes, which are often not eco-friendly. Such urban freight movement worsens traffic conditions, noise levels, and air quality, which particularly affects disadvantaged communities, where logistic facilities may be concentrated owing to lower property rates. While, such relocation of logistics closer to the urban core also provides opportunities for the use of zero-emission vehicles in last-mile distributions, however, a significant change in the carrier’s fleet can take a considerable amount of time, while there is an urgent need for operational improvement initiatives that could provide efficient alternatives to address global climate change and local pollution impacts. Towards this end, carriers accounting for emissions in their routing decisions (explicit eco-routing), or policy initiatives that can incentivize carriers to implicitly consider the impact of their emissions in their routing decisions (implicit eco-routing) could make more immediate contributions to solving the imminent environmental crisis. Thus, in this blog we explore the opportunities and challenges associated with eco-routing for carriers in the form of the private impacts of eco-routing, and for regulators in the form of the system-wide impacts of network-wide eco-routing in the Southern California Association of Governments (SCAG) region (see figure below).</p> <div class="row mt-3" style="text-align: center"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/13.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="60%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p style="font-size:0.7em; text-align: center">Southern California Association of Governments (SCAG) region – network and census tracts</p> <p>To begin with, as with many such green initiatives, we found a lack of incentive for the carrier to eco-route its fleet and account for emissions in its decision-making (explicit eco-routing). Thus, while eco-routing does indeed reduce emissions, the resulting increase in cost to the carrier dissuades the carrier from eco-routing. However, it is important to note that this result is not surprising, since if eco-routing were to result in a reduction in cost, the carrier would have been eco-routing in the first place. Instead, it is important for regulators to consider the potential opportunities wherein the carrier can be incentivized to eco-route. For instance, the carriers routing their fleet on the shortest path observe a substantial reduction in travel time and fuel consumption from eco-routing and thus could be encouraged to eco-route with few monetary incentives. Moreover, considering the overlap between certain conventional routing options (fastest and least cost paths) and eco-routing options, appropriate policy initiatives could encourage the carrier to consider the impact of its criteria pollutant and greenhouse gas emissions. Further, the benefits from eco-routing are best realized in off-peak hours when there are fewer passenger cars in the network. Thus, policy interventions that target such opportunities can instigate the carrier to eco-route and therefore reduce freight-related externalities (see figure below). However, regulators must note that policy measures that incentivize carriers to reduce fuel consumption may not result in reduction in emissions, as is otherwise assumed.</p> <div class="row mt-3" style="text-align: center"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/14.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="75%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p style="font-size:0.7em; text-align: center">Reduction in emissions in Southern California Association of Governments (SCAG) region from network-wide freight eco-routing</p> <p>Considering these results, regulators must appropriately valuate emissions for carriers in their policy interventions to ensure an appropriate response from the carriers. Such measures could include mandating carriers to undertake regular training and assessment of their drivers for eco-driving behavior as a prerequisite to subsidies, permits, licenses, etc. In fact, from the regulator’s perspective it is important to consider eco-routing from an equity perspective rather than from a purely monetary perspective. In general, we found a lack of incentive for stakeholders to encourage carriers to eco-route and to account for their externalities in their routing decisions. Nonetheless, these results assume that the benefits from reduced exposure to emissions to be homogeneous across the population, when perhaps such benefits are heterogeneous, with potentially greater benefits from reducing externalities realized for disadvantaged communities in the region than for the population in general. To this end, the regulator could geofence certain disadvantaged communities and restrict carriers’ access to such neighborhoods (implicit eco-routing). This results in the geofenced region observing a significant reduction in externalities, albeit with increased passenger traffic and a marginal but equitable increase in externalities elsewhere. Moreover, the disadvantaged communities other than those within the geofence could also observe a reduction in externalities, particularly criteria pollutant emissions that have an adverse effect on human health. And beyond reductions in emissions, eco-routing reduces driver fatigue by avoiding heavy acceleration and braking events, especially for drivers routing their trucks for expedited service, and can therefore reduce traffic accidents. Thus, overall, freight eco-routing has the potential to reduce transportation-related externalities equitably, and consequently to bridge the gap in transition to zero-emissions as adoption of alternate cleaner modes of distribution gathers pace, through appropriate policy measures that create incentives to encourage eco-routing.</p>]]></content><author><name>Anmol Pahwa</name></author><category term="moving-goods"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Freight transportation is fundamental to economic growth, nonetheless, the trucks that haul this freight are pollution intensive, emitting greenhouse gases that affect the health of our planet, and criteria pollutants that adversely affect human health, and are also one of the leading cause for urban congestion and accidents. Can eco-routing trucks reduce freight related externalities? In this blog, we explore the opportunities and challenges in freight eco-routing.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding last-mile distribution resilience</title><link href="https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2022/resilience/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding last-mile distribution resilience"/><published>2022-07-22T13:52:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-22T13:52:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2022/resilience</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2022/resilience/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>How resilient is last-mile distribution? Coping with low-probability high-severity disruption.</strong></p> <p>In the years prior to the pandemic, consumer shopping trends had seen a steady and significant shift towards online retail. Despite the prevalence of e-commerce platforms with lucrative shopping offers for consumers, traditional in-store shopping still dominated daily consumer purchases. Nonetheless, more and more consumers had been engaging in omnichannel behavior, with product search, trial, and final purchase occurring in different channels. However, the COVID-19 pandemic significantly inhibited public movement, and an unprecedented number of consumers, including many first-time users, took to e-commerce platforms for the purchase of critical goods, daily essentials, groceries, medications, and health-care products. The figure below showcases this shift in consumer shopping behavior due to the COVID-19 pandemic in the US in the form of increase in e-commerce transactions for the first half of 2020. Beyond the typical business-to-consumer (B2C) services, some e-retailers also delivered personal protective equipment, including gowns, masks, and gloves to frontline healthcare services. Typically, these e-retailers account for only minor day-to-day and seasonal disruptions and thereby design their distribution structures for low-cost just-in-time deliveries, thus leaving the supply-chain vulnerable to such severe and unforeseen disruptions. Given the role of e-retailers in supply of essential goods not only to the typical customer but also to frontline services, in this blog we assess last-mile distribution resilience in terms of an e-retailer’s ability to maintain and efficiently restore level of service in the event of such a low-probability high-severity disruption.</p> <div class="row mt-3" style="text-align: center"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/11.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="50%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p style="font-size:0.7em; text-align: center">E-commerce demand surge in the early months of the COVID-19 pandemic</p> <p>To cope with low-probability high-severity disruptions, we assumed that the e-retailer outsources part of its operations via one of the many outsourcing channels available, namely, with crowdsourced fleet of light-duty trucks, or collection-points for customer pickup (lockers), or via a logistics service provider operating from micro-hubs using a fleet of electric cargo-bikes (see figure below). The crowdsourced operations take their inspiration from the Amazon Flex program, and thus, much like the e-retailer’s delivery trucks, the crowdsourced drivers collect packages at the e-commerce fulfillment facility before embarking on e-retailer designed delivery tours. However, for collection-point pickup, the e-retailer must fulfill the collection-points using its fleet of delivery trucks before customers can travel to one of the collection-points to collect their packages. Similarly, when the e-retailer outsources part of its distribution via a logistics service provider, the e-retailer must fulfill the logistics service provider’s micro-hubs using its fleet of delivery trucks before the cargo-bikes from these micro-hubs can embark for last-mile deliveries.</p> <div class="row mt-3" style="text-align: center"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/12.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="75%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p style="font-size:0.7em; text-align: center">Last-mile distribution operations (e-retailer and outsourcing channel combined distribution structure) </p> <p>Considering the opportunities and challenges we explored with the different outsourcing channels, we found that it could be useful to establish crowdsourced deliveries to cope with low severity disruptions, deploy backup distribution for moderately severe disruptions, and encourage customers to self-collect packages to cope with high severity disruptions. Nonetheless, the e-retailer must carry out appropriate pre-disruption planning to create suitable platforms and incentives to ensure reliable crowdsourced deliveries, position sufficient number of lockers near residential areas to ensure customer willingness to self-collect packages, and negotiate contracts with several logistics service providers to ensure backup last-mile distribution. Moreover, as the disruption evolves, the e-retailer must gauge the availability of crowdsourced drivers, the willingness of customers to self-collect packages, and the capability of the logistics service providers to ensure functionality of its distribution channel, so that the e-retailer can deploy the appropriate outsourcing channel(s) during the different phases of the disruption. And finally, as the disruption recedes, the e-retailer must re-engage strategic and tactical decision-making process not only to restore the level of service efficiently and in a timely manner, but also to plan ahead for a changed post-disruption landscape. Moreover, consistent with other studies in the resilience literature, this work highlights the need for organizational, social, economic, and engineering units of last-mile distribution to consistently perform pre-disruption mitigation, appropriately respond during the disruption, and efficiently carry out post-disruption analysis and recovery for last-mile distribution to be resilient to disruption. Continuing the discussion from the previous blog, our work highlights the need to develop not only sustainable last-mile distribution structure that can render economically viable, environmentally friendly, and socially equitable operations capable to cope with high-probability low-severity fluctuations in the delivery environment, but also resilient last-mile distribution structure that is robust, redundant, resourceful, and rapid against low-probability high-severity disruptions.</p>]]></content><author><name>Anmol Pahwa</name></author><category term="moving-goods"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How resilient is last-mile distribution? Coping with low-probability high-severity disruption.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Last-mile distribution in the pandemic</title><link href="https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2022/pandemic/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Last-mile distribution in the pandemic"/><published>2022-07-01T15:19:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-01T15:19:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2022/pandemic</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2022/pandemic/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>How did the pandemic affect e-commerce operations? Understanding resilience in the context of last-mile distribution sustainability.</strong></p> <p>On 11th March 2020, the World Health Organization declared the novel coronavirus outbreak as a pandemic. The days thereafter saw governments around the world establish contingency plans with lock-downs announced to contain the spread of virus. This ushered a frenzy of purchase and hoarding of daily essentials leading to supply shortage at local brick and mortar stores. However, the fear of virus contraction also made shopping in-store inconvenient and stressful. This nudged many consumers to shop online instead, leading to a significant rise in e-commerce demand, particularly for specific range of products. While e-retailers design their operations to absorb variations in demand which are typically high-probability low-severity fluctuations (such as holiday season demand), this surge in demand, a low-probability high-severity fluctuation, gave little time to the e-retailer to re-organize and re-evaluate its operations. Thus, to cater to this unprecedented surge in demand, e-retailers had to scale up their operations constrained to pre-pandemic level of resources, thereby operating at a lower level of service with high lead times, delivery failures and demand prioritization. This pandemic thus motivates research in developing resilient last-mile distribution that can resist, absorb, and recover from such low-probability high severity disruptive events.</p> <div class="row mt-3" style="text-align: center"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="50%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p style="font-size:0.7em; text-align: center">Demand surge during the pandemic</p> <p style="font-size:0.7em; text-align: center">The two vertical dashed line represent disruption start (day 18) and disruption end (day 114)</p> <p>Before we begin our discussion on resilient distribution, let’s take a look at a dictionary-esque definition of resilience. Resilience – a term common to disaster management, is the ability of social units to mitigate hazard, contain the effects of disaster when they occur, carry out recovery activities in ways that minimize social disruption, and mitigate the effects of future disaster. Typically, when a system is exposed to a disruption, its performance metrics fall, then plateau, before recovering back to a certain extent (as shown in the figure below). This system response is modeled and quantified using resilience triangles in conjunction with the R4 framework. The R4 framework formalizes the dictionary definition of resilience into four attributes of resilience, namely, Robustness (ability to absorb), Redundancy (ability to substitute for disrupted elements within the system), Resourcefulness (ability to diagnose and initiate solution), and Rapidity (ability to recover timely). The resilience triangles quantify these attributes for tangible and meaningful analysis of system’s response to disruption (see figure below). In particular, 1) Robustness is defined as the height of the performance curve at peak performance loss, 2) Redundancy is quantified as the average rate of performance decay, 3) Resourcefulness metric represents the ratio of recovered performance to peak loss, and 4) Rapidity, like Redundancy, identifies the average rate of recovery. The disruption, system’s response, and the four metrics are detailed in the figure below.</p> <div class="row mt-3" style="text-align: center"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/4.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="75%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p style="font-size:0.7em; text-align: center">Modeling system’s response to disruption using resilience triangles and the R4 framework</p> <p><strong>Case Study</strong></p> <p>In the context of last-mile distribution, this work defines resilience as the ability of the e-retailer to maintain satisfactory level of freight flow in the event of disruption, and recover efficiently with minimal use of resources – time, capital, and human effort. Based on the above discussion, this study introduces two performance metrics – a Level of Service (LOS) metric representing the ratio of served to total demand, and a Level of Efficiency (LOE) metric representing ratio of cost of operating under normal conditions to the cost of operating under disruption. Notice, these metrics are consistent with definition of resilience introduced in the context of last-mile distribution. The former identifies level of freight flow while the latter represents use of resources. Prior to the disruption, this work assumes operations of an e-retailer serving 30000 customers located randomly and uniformly in a service region of size 475 sq. mi., using diesel trucks from an e-commerce fulfillment facility. Given a time-horizon of 10 years and 9 working hours in a day, the objective of the e-retailer is to optimize its strategic and tactical operations so as to minimize the total cost of last-mile delivery. Such a design of last-mile distribution structure is consistent with the lean management principles of supply-chain design. In the event of a disruption, the e-retailer observes a demand shock (peak demand of 47,500 customers). Due to lean design of the last-mile distribution structure, e-retailer has no redundant capacity. Thus, to meet daily demand, e-retailer has to outsource the demand over capacity, which this work describes as surge-outsourcing. This outsourcing channel can be crowdsourced drivers crowd-shipping delivery, or a 3rd party delivery service provider. Any unmet demand above the capacity of the combined distribution structure is served the next day. This work penalizes the e-retailer for this unmet demand. Post-disruption, the e-retailer again observes a stable level of demand – 36000, and thus re-optimizes its operations so as to minimize the total cost of last-mile delivery.</p> <p>To evaluate delivery tour length and travel time, establish customers served per delivery tour, number of tours per delivery vehicles, fleet size, and associated fixed, operation and emission cost, a last-mile distribution model is developed using Continuous Approximation (CA) methods.</p> <p>Below are the LOS and LOE performance curves, and related resilience metrics for the three scenarios, 1) no surge-outsourcing (None), 2) surge-outsourcing via crowd-shipped drivers (Crowd-shipping), and 3) surge-outsourcing via 3rd party carrier (Outsourcing).</p> <div class="row mt-3" style="text-align: center"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/5.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="75%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/6.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="75%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p style="font-size:0.7em; text-align: center">Level of Service (LOS) and Efficiency (LOE) without any surge-outsourcing</p> <div class="row mt-3" style="text-align: center"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/7.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="75%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/8.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="75%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p style="font-size:0.7em; text-align: center">Level of Service (LOS) and Efficiency (LOE) with crowd-shipping</p> <div class="row mt-3" style="text-align: center"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/9.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="75%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/10.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="75%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p style="font-size:0.7em; text-align: center">Level of Service (LOS) and Efficiency (LOE) with delivery outsourcing (3rd party delivery service provider)</p> <p>In operations research, and in general in systems design, the prime objective is to develop an economically viable and a socially equitable system with minimal externalities (three fundamental pillars of sustainability). However, certain systems and environments may be exposed uncertain elements, such as daily demand, traffic speeds, etc. for a last-mile delivery distribution system. Such stochastic systems are designed with additional investments and protections so as to minimize the likelihood of failure. However, a more robust, and a more sustainable system can be developed by embracing resilience as one of the fundamental pillars of sustainability. The above developed framework aids in quantifying resilience in the form of system’s ability to absorb consequences of disruption (Robustness), system’s ability to replace affected elements in the event of a disruption (Redundancy), system’s ability to initiate solutions toward recovery with minimal use of resources (Resourcefulness), and system’s ability to recover timely (Rapidity). The benefits of designing not only sustainable but resilient system can be evidenced from the case study developed in this work. Under normal working conditions, e-retailer benefits from owning a fleet of diesel trucks and keeping delivery operations in-house as it allows efficient consolidation and operations. The total cost per package to serve pre-disruption demand (30,000 customers) turns out to be $1.68 when the e-retailer deploys its own fleet, $2.38 when the all the packages are instead crowd-shipped, and $2.64 if the e-retailer decides to outsource delivery via a 3rd party carrier. However, to be able to surge-outsource part of its operations in case of disruption (be it low-probability high-severity or high-probability low-severity) allows for a more resilient distribution structure, as can be seen from the figures above. This shows that a “sustainable” system may not be resilient (and also vice-versa, though this is of less significance), and that there may be a tradeoff between “sustainability” and resilience, or in case of last-mile distribution, there may be a tradeoff between designing lean vs. resilient system, thus bolstering the argument for embracing resilience in sustainable design.</p>]]></content><author><name>Anmol Pahwa</name></author><category term="moving-goods"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How did the pandemic affect e-commerce operations? Understanding resilience in the context of last-mile distribution sustainability.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is the environmental costs of expedited shipping?</title><link href="https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2020/expeditedshipping/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is the environmental costs of expedited shipping?"/><published>2020-02-05T13:23:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-05T13:23:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2020/expeditedshipping</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2020/expeditedshipping/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Get it delivered in 3 days, by tomorrow!, today!! We have often given into this instant gratification, though for a premium, but what is the real cost of expedited deliveries?</strong></p> <p>This blog is in continuation to an earlier blog –<a href="https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2019/onlineshopping/"> Is online shopping environment friendly? </a>If you haven’t already checked that out, I would recommend you pause here, read the earlier blog and come back to enjoy this one.</p> <p>In the early days of online shopping, I remember getting packages delivered to my home in about a week or two from the day of purchase. In logistics jargon, this is called lead-time. During those days, my online purchases would pertain to things I knew I couldn’t get anywhere near me, such as PlayStation game disc maybe. But sometime during the last 7 years, my online cart has gradually transformed from having things I knew I cannot get anywhere near me, to things I know are easily available around, but I would rather save the time and effort of the travel. This bolsters the idea that travel is a derived demand, i.e. we travel not for the sake of it but for some other purpose, and hence if we can get that bag of groceries delivered to our door step, then we might as well. Coming back to lead-time, this change in shopping cart, from maybe not so essential to more essential and daily-use items has induced a need to get things as early as possible, thus reducing the lead-time available. This surely has affected the way supply-chains organize and consolidate themselves, but what are the impacts on the end-user (and the community in general) beyond the premium you paid for the expedited delivery?</p> <p>Before we look into the numbers, lets first understand what happens when temporal constraints become stricter. Generally speaking, the more time available at the e-retailer’s disposal, the better can the delivery tours be planned, i.e. the e-retailer can consolidate as much demand as possible and thus better utilize the capacity of the delivery vehicle. And hence it is argued that since e-retailers consolidate the demand, and optimize the routes, e-commerce can reduce shopping travel related negative externalities. However, any such benefits were wiped out by rush deliveries as it compels the e-retailers to ship packages at lower consolidation levels. Thus, it can be argued that temporal constraints compel the e-retailers to plan higher amounts of shorter tours which essentially increases the distances driven, thereby increasing costs and emissions.</p> <p>In particular, the number of deliveries made in a tour could go down from 300 to 10 – a reduction of 97%. Further, vehicle miles traveled (VMT) per package, often used to understand impacts on congestion, could go up from 0.2 mi to 1.4 mi, about 7 times as much. Consequently, urban goods distritbution could witness substantial increase in externalities such as greenhouse gas and criteria pollutant emissions. Moreover, in monetary terms, the cost of distribution for the e-retailer could go up from $1.8 to $7.2, which could either be transferred onto the customer as a premium for faster delivery, or could be subsidized to gain larger market shares. However, beyond the premium, the increased emissions and congestion results in an externality cost to the society, which could go up from $0.1 per package to $0.7 per package, a hike of about 7 times.</p> <p>To conclude, it can be argued that last-mile deliveries are logistically efficient and can produce savings in cost and externalities in comparison to shopping in-store. However, the recent trends in last-mile delivery, such as expedited and time-window based deliveries, especially observed in the e-grocery and food delivery segment of e-commerce, seem to be environmentally unsustainable. Yet, more and more firms today offer such lucrative offers in order to capture larger market shares, and generate larger revenue and profit. Although not discussed here, free returns is yet another way in which e-retailers pursue larger market share. The tendency to return a product is not founded in the functional error of the product but can be ascribed to lack of information about the fit and suitability of a product. The apparel segment especially observes high rate of return, which can go as high as 45%, i.e. almost every other product is returned. And although reverse logistics incur additional operational cost (also emissions) to the e-retailer, not providing free return puts the retailer at the risk of losing the customer. This compels the e-retailer to provide free return, face the additional operational cost, produce more emissions just to keep the consumer happy. Hence, in general, one can conclude that the environmental efficiency of deliveries reduces significantly as companies make such lucrative offers to its consumers. The above results and discussion therefore highlights the importance of stakeholders, in particular, for consumers in consolidating their demand, for e-retailers in consolidating the deliveries, and for planners and regulators in managing the urban freight system to foster sustainability.</p>]]></content><author><name>Anmol Pahwa</name></author><category term="moving-goods"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Get it delivered in 3 days, by tomorrow!, today!! We have often given into this instant gratification, though for a premium, but what is the real cost of expedited deliveries?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Uber vs. car, taxi, or transit?</title><link href="https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2019/uber/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Uber vs. car, taxi, or transit?"/><published>2019-08-18T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-18T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2019/uber</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2019/uber/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>There is demand, there is supply, and then there is Uber, connecting the two like never before. While on one hand, Uber provides accessible and affordable mobility, its influence on individual’s decision making has potential consequences on car ownership, driver jobs and transit ridership. Lets dive into each one of them in this blog.</strong></p> <p>The last couple of decades has witnessed a radical change in the transportation sector, be it for moving the people or moving goods. With e-commerce transforming our shopping experience and ride-hailing services, also known as Transportation Network Company (TNC), influencing our commute, the on-demand economy has become an integral part of our lives today. In the US alone, the TNC ridership amounted for 4.2 billion trips in 2018, a growth of ~62% from 2017. This increasing shift towards an on-demand mobility service competes with car, traditional taxis and transit in terms of car ownership, driver jobs and transit ridership. Before we understand what these impacts are, lets take a look at who are the adapters of the on-demand economy and who is most influenced by it.</p> <div class="row mt-3" style="text-align: center"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="75%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="row mt-3" style="text-align: center"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="75%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>The above two figures present user demographics and user adaption rates for the two on-demand services – ride-hailing and e-commerce. As an example, the first figure tells us that 52% of the people who used ride-hailing service were males, while the second figure tells us that 9% of the males used the ride-hailing service. An important point to note here is that despite of the obvious convenience of on-demand services, the elderly population, for whom it is touted to be the most useful, least uses it, potentially due to lack of experience with smart phones and on-demand economy. However, the key takeaway from the above two figures is the striking similarity of the highs and the lows of user demographics and adaption for ride-hailing and online shopping. Thus the market for the two on-demand services is similar, i.e. those who tend to shop on Amazon also tend to use Uber. And although, ride-hailing and online shopping both together will influence individual’s decision making, in this blog we only look at the impacts from ride-hailing service on car ownership, taxi-driver jobs and transit ridership.</p> <p><strong>vs. Car</strong></p> <p>For most people buying a car is the highest investment they make after buying a house. But with the advent of on-demand taxi services like Uber, not owning a car might as well be a smart decision. With that being said, in a study performed at UC Davis, on an aggregate the authors did not find any significant reduction in vehicle ownership for ride-hailing users. However, there was considerable heterogeneity within this information, and the study found that the more frequent users of ride-hailing service did indeed have a lower vehicle ownership compared to less frequent users. The study found similar results for self-reported change in personal vehicle usage (in terms of vehicle miles driven), i.e. more frequent users of ride-hailing service drove less with their personal cars. Thus the opportunity cost from an idle sitting car gives more reasons to dispose off or rent out the asset.</p> <p><strong>vs. Taxi</strong></p> <p>The conventional taxi service sector is a highly regulated one in the US, limiting number of taxis and fare in the city. However, Uber, for as much as it may seem like, is not considered as a taxi-company, primarily because Uber is just a platform that connects customer demand for travel with driver supply. And hence it can easily flout the taxi regulations. Thus the entry of Uber in the field renders similar impacts as if the taxi-service sector was de-regulated. In particular, Berger et al. study the impacts of Uber entry on taxi driver jobs and compare the effects with 1978 Airline Deregulation Act and Motor Carrier Act 1980. As with the previous two deregulation acts, this study also found a decrease in driver wages by about 10% due to Uber entry, however, the total taxi driver supply remained unaffected. Specifically , the wage-employed drivers are worse affected compared to the self-employed drivers, who could switch once Uber entered the market.</p> <p><strong>vs. Transit</strong></p> <p>While above we looked at the interplay of Uber with Car and Taxi, with transit however, the interplay is unique. Uber provides obvious benefits with its reliability, convenience and accessibility. With that being said, transit can be cheaper, especially for daily commute purpose. And hence, Uber can be an alternate mode to transit – thus substituting for it, or can even complement transit for the first and last-mile of the travel. This interplay is sensitive to individual’s behavior in terms of value for time, money, convenience and safety. It is easy to think of Uber as a substitute to transit, however, if Uber cannot produce significant time savings compared to transit such that it outdoes its additional cost, Uber is very likely to be a complement to transit. Largely, the literature has found strong correlation between transit use and Uber use, however no causal inference has been deduced yet. In particular, a study conducted in the US found transit usage to be positively affected by Uber entry, increasing ridership by as much as 5% especially for transit systems in bigger cities, however with some significant difference in this effect for rail based and bus based transit systems. Yet there are certain studies who have reported substitution effect as users of ride-hailing service reported the next best alternative to be public transit.</p> <p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p> <p>Whether one likes Uber or not, it is likely to dominate the market for long. While it can have potential benefits by reducing vehicle ownership and complementing for transit, it has had disruptive impacts on taxi-service sector. And it is important to note, that even if car ownership does go down and if indeed Uber does complement transit, it can induce demand leading to worsening of traffic related externalities like congestion and pollution. Understanding the impacts of Uber is hence essential for policy makers so that cities can implement policies that can minimize the disruptive impacts without inhibiting individual mobility.</p>]]></content><author><name>Anmol Pahwa</name></author><category term="moving-people"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There is demand, there is supply, and then there is Uber, connecting the two like never before. While on one hand, Uber provides accessible and affordable mobility, its influence on individual’s decision making has potential consequences on car ownership, driver jobs and transit ridership. Lets dive into each one of them in this blog.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is online shopping environment friendly?</title><link href="https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2019/onlineshopping/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is online shopping environment friendly?"/><published>2019-08-02T16:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-02T16:03:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2019/onlineshopping</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lognitilab.github.io/blog/2019/onlineshopping/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Should I visit a store or should I just check out Amazon? You might have asked yourself this question quite a few times by now. But have you ever considered the impacts of this decision on the environment? Well, this article should help you make an informed decision next time.</strong></p> <p>August 11, 1994 marks the day when the first ever online transaction was made, and since then, the internet has continuously reshaped the way we shop. E-commerce, a term completely unknown to us a couple of decades ago, has gradually become a fundamental part of our daily lives.</p> <p>With the increasing influence of internet on our decisions as to what and when to shop, how and how much to shop, the underlying question posed onto us is whether online shopping is good for us? i.e. whether online shopping is substituting (replacing) or complementing (co-existing with) in-store shopping? The literature on this largely weighs towards the complementary behavior, thus arguing for an increased travel activity, one from the delivery vans serving the online retail demand, and the other from the personal trips to stores. Yet another aspect of online shopping is the induced demand – an increase in number of purchases made by a consumer, be it online or in-store. Remember this, because it will come to bite us later.</p> <p>To answer the question posed above, I modeled the shopping choice – whether to shop online, to shop in-store, or to not shop at all, with socioeconomic parameters of the individual (such as age, income, education level etc.), city related parameters and some other temporal parameters. The resulting model tells us which factors influence one’s choice to shop online or in-store, or not shop at all. This dis-aggregate model was then applied over the synthetically generated population of the city of San Francisco (SF) to determine people who shop in-store and/or online. The resulting externalities, i.e. traffic in terms of vehicle miles traveled (VMT), and pollution in terms of greenhouse gas emissions (CO and CO<sub>2</sub>), as well as criteria pollutant emissions (NO<sub>x</sub> and PM) were estimated from the shopping related travel.</p> <p>First, I present here one-to-one direct comparison of externalities from in-store and online shopping in terms of equivalence of one with the other, i.e. how many online purchases produce the same amount of externalities as the in-store purchase. Turns out, around 8 online purchases produce as much vehicle travel as 1 in-store purchase, thus reducing the traffic. Consequently, if everyone was to only shop online, significant reduction in emissions can be produced, barring NO<sub>x</sub> emissions. Note, delivery trucks are heavy emitters of criteria pollutant emissions, especially NO<sub>x</sub> emissions.</p> <pre><code class="language-echarts">{
  "title": {
    "text": "Comparison of in-store and online shopping"
  },
  "responsive": true,
  "tooltip": {},
  "xAxis": {
    "data": ["VMT", "CO", "CO2", "PM", "NOx"]
  },
  "yAxis": {},
  "series": [
    {
      "name": "ratio of in-store to online",
      "type": "bar",
      "data": [8.1, 7.8, 2.7, 1.8, 0.8]
    }
  ]
}
</code></pre> <p><br/> Having established a direct one-to-one comparison, I then estimated the impact of online shopping accounting for the consumer behavior through the shopping choice model. Note, the current omni-channel retail scenario implies that some people shop in-store while others shop online. The results showcase a 7% reduction in overall VMT due to online purchases. Consequently, the urban environment witnesses a significant reduction in emissions, barring of course the NO<sub>x</sub> emissions.</p> <pre><code class="language-echarts">{
  "title": {
    "text": "Impact of online shopping"
  },
  "responsive": true,
  "tooltip": {},
  "xAxis": {
    "data": ["VMT", "CO", "CO2", "PM", "NOx"]
  },
  "yAxis": {},
  "series": [
    {
      "name": "percentage change",
      "type": "bar",
      "data": [7.0, 7.0, 4.9, 3.4, -1.8]
    }
  ]
}
</code></pre> <p><br/> These results therefore pose the question, why push for cleaner freight movement? Well, because these results are founded on current consumer behavior and retailer practices. It is important to consider the potential impact on consumer behavior as e-commerce can induce demand and conseuqently vehicle travel. Further, consumer-focused retail practices with lucrative offers such as expedited shipping and free returns render frequent less-than-truckloads goods flow. Hence, while e-commerce has the potential to offer environmentally efficient means of goods distribution, changing consumer behavior and retailer practices puts sustianability of urban goods flow at risk.</p> <p>To conclude, what can you do the next time you have to shop? The direct comparison of in-store and online shopping showcase benefits of online shopping. Hence, you could try to replace your trips to store with online shopping. Further, you could try to consolidate your needs into a single purchase, enabling the e-retailer to make fewer vehicle trips to your house. With this I hope you can make an informed decision the next time you shop.</p>]]></content><author><name>Anmol Pahwa</name></author><category term="moving-goods"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Should I visit a store or should I just check out Amazon? You might have asked yourself this question quite a few times by now. But have you ever considered the impacts of this decision on the environment Well, this article should help you make an informed decision next time.]]></summary></entry></feed>