<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://anmol1104.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://anmol1104.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-04-04T07:11:27+00:00</updated><id>https://anmol1104.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">LogNiti Lab</title><subtitle>Academic Profile </subtitle><entry><title type="html">What is the environmental costs of expedited shipping?</title><link href="https://anmol1104.github.io/blog/2020/expeditedshipping/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is the environmental costs of expedited shipping?"/><published>2020-02-05T13:23:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-05T13:23:00+00:00</updated><id>https://anmol1104.github.io/blog/2020/expeditedshipping</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anmol1104.github.io/blog/2020/expeditedshipping/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Get it delivered in 3 days, by tomorrow!, today!! We have often given into this instant gratification, though for a premium, but what is the real cost of expedited deliveries?</strong></p> <p>This blog is in continuation to an earlier blog –<a href="https://anmol1104.github.io/blog/2019/onlineshopping/"> Is online shopping environment friendly? </a>If you haven’t already checked that out, I would recommend you pause here, read the earlier blog and come back to enjoy this one.</p> <p>In the early days of online shopping, I remember getting packages delivered to my home in about a week or two from the day of purchase. In logistics jargon, this is called lead-time. During those days, my online purchases would pertain to things I knew I couldn’t get anywhere near me, such as PlayStation game disc maybe. But sometime during the last 7 years, my online cart has gradually transformed from having things I knew I cannot get anywhere near me, to things I know are easily available around, but I would rather save the time and effort of the travel. This bolsters the idea that travel is a derived demand, i.e. we travel not for the sake of it but for some other purpose, and hence if we can get that bag of groceries delivered to our door step, then we might as well. Coming back to lead-time, this change in shopping cart, from maybe not so essential to more essential and daily-use items has induced a need to get things as early as possible, thus reducing the lead-time available. This surely has affected the way supply-chains organize and consolidate themselves, but what are the impacts on the end-user (and the community in general) beyond the premium you paid for the expedited delivery?</p> <p>Before we look into the numbers, lets first understand what happens when temporal constraints become stricter. Generally speaking, the more time available at the e-retailer’s disposal, the better can the delivery tours be planned, i.e. the e-retailer can consolidate as much demand as possible and thus better utilize the capacity of the delivery vehicle. And hence it is argued that since e-retailers consolidate the demand, and optimize the routes, e-commerce can reduce shopping travel related negative externalities. However, any such benefits were wiped out by rush deliveries as it compels the e-retailers to ship packages at lower consolidation levels. Thus, it can be argued that temporal constraints compel the e-retailers to plan higher amounts of shorter tours which essentially increases the distances driven, thereby increasing costs and emissions.</p> <p>In particular, the number of deliveries made in a tour could go down from 300 to 10 – a reduction of 97%. Further, vehicle miles traveled (VMT) per package, often used to understand impacts on congestion, could go up from 0.2 mi to 1.4 mi, about 7 times as much. Consequently, urban goods distritbution could witness substantial increase in externalities such as greenhouse gas and criteria pollutant emissions. Moreover, in monetary terms, the cost of distribution for the e-retailer could go up from $1.8 to $7.2, which could either be transferred onto the customer as a premium for faster delivery, or could be subsidized to gain larger market shares. However, beyond the premium, the increased emissions and congestion results in an externality cost to the society, which could go up from $0.1 per package to $0.7 per package, a hike of about 7 times.</p> <p>To conclude, it can be argued that last-mile deliveries are logistically efficient and can produce savings in cost and externalities in comparison to shopping in-store. However, the recent trends in last-mile delivery, such as expedited and time-window based deliveries, especially observed in the e-grocery and food delivery segment of e-commerce, seem to be environmentally unsustainable. Yet, more and more firms today offer such lucrative offers in order to capture larger market shares, and generate larger revenue and profit. Although not discussed here, free returns is yet another way in which e-retailers pursue larger market share. The tendency to return a product is not founded in the functional error of the product but can be ascribed to lack of information about the fit and suitability of a product. The apparel segment especially observes high rate of return, which can go as high as 45%, i.e. almost every other product is returned. And although reverse logistics incur additional operational cost (also emissions) to the e-retailer, not providing free return puts the retailer at the risk of losing the customer. This compels the e-retailer to provide free return, face the additional operational cost, produce more emissions just to keep the consumer happy. Hence, in general, one can conclude that the environmental efficiency of deliveries reduces significantly as companies make such lucrative offers to its consumers. The above results and discussion therefore highlights the importance of stakeholders, in particular, for consumers in consolidating their demand, for e-retailers in consolidating the deliveries, and for planners and regulators in managing the urban freight system to foster sustainability.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="moving-goods"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Get it delivered in 3 days, by tomorrow!, today!! We have often given into this instant gratification, though for a premium, but what is the real cost of expedited deliveries?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is online shopping environment friendly?</title><link href="https://anmol1104.github.io/blog/2019/onlineshopping/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is online shopping environment friendly?"/><published>2019-08-02T16:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-02T16:03:00+00:00</updated><id>https://anmol1104.github.io/blog/2019/onlineshopping</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anmol1104.github.io/blog/2019/onlineshopping/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Should I visit a store or should I just check out Amazon? You might have asked yourself this question quite a few times by now. But have you ever considered the impacts of this decision on the environment? Well, this article should help you make an informed decision next time.</strong></p> <p>August 11, 1994 marks the day when the first ever online transaction was made, and since then, the internet has continuously reshaped the way we shop. E-commerce, a term completely unknown to us a couple of decades ago, has gradually become a fundamental part of our daily lives.</p> <p>With the increasing influence of internet on our decisions as to what and when to shop, how and how much to shop, the underlying question posed onto us is whether online shopping is good for us? i.e. whether online shopping is substituting (replacing) or complementing (co-existing with) in-store shopping? The literature on this largely weighs towards the complementary behavior, thus arguing for an increased travel activity, one from the delivery vans serving the online retail demand, and the other from the personal trips to stores. Yet another aspect of online shopping is the induced demand – an increase in number of purchases made by a consumer, be it online or in-store. Remember this, because it will come to bite us later.</p> <p>To answer the question posed above, I modeled the shopping choice – whether to shop online, to shop in-store, or to not shop at all, with socioeconomic parameters of the individual (such as age, income, education level etc.), city related parameters and some other temporal parameters. The resulting model tells us which factors influence one’s choice to shop online or in-store, or not shop at all. This dis-aggregate model was then applied over the synthetically generated population of the city of San Francisco (SF) to determine people who shop in-store and/or online. The resulting externalities, i.e. traffic in terms of vehicle miles traveled (VMT), and pollution in terms of greenhouse gas emissions (CO and CO2), as well as criteria pollutant emissions (NOx and PM) were estimated from the shopping related travel.</p> <p>First, I present here one-to-one direct comparison of externalities from in-store and online shopping in terms of equivalence of one with the other, i.e. how many online purchases produce the same amount of externalities as the in-store purchase. Turns out, around 8 online purchases produce as much vehicle travel as 1 in-store purchase, thus reducing the traffic. Consequently, if everyone was to only shop online, significant reduction in emissions can be produced, barring NOx emissions. Note, delivery trucks are heavy emitters of criteria pollutant emissions, especially NOx emissions.</p> <pre><code class="language-echarts">{
  "title": {
    "text": "Comparison of in-store and online shopping"
  },
  "responsive": true,
  "tooltip": {},
  "xAxis": {
    "data": ["VMT", "CO", "CO2", "PM", "NOx"]
  },
  "yAxis": {},
  "series": [
    {
      "name": "ratio of in-store to online",
      "type": "bar",
      "data": [8.1, 7.8, 2.7, 1.8, 0.8]
    }
  ]
}
</code></pre> <p>Having established a direct one-to-one comparison, I then estimated the impact of online shopping accounting for the consumer behavior through the shopping choice model. Note, the current omni-channel retail scenario implies that some people shop in-store while others shop online. The results showcase a 7% reduction in overall VMT due to online purchases. Consequently, the urban environment witnesses a significant reduction in emissions, barring of course the NOx emissions.</p> <pre><code class="language-echarts">{
  "title": {
    "text": "Impact of online shopping"
  },
  "responsive": true,
  "tooltip": {},
  "xAxis": {
    "data": ["VMT", "CO", "CO2", "PM", "NOx"]
  },
  "yAxis": {},
  "series": [
    {
      "name": "percentage change",
      "type": "bar",
      "data": [7.0, 7.0, 4.9, 3.4, -1.8]
    }
  ]
}
</code></pre> <p>These results therefore pose the question, why push for cleaner freight movement? Well, because these results are founded on current consumer behavior and retailer practices. It is important to consider the potential impact on consumer behavior as e-commerce can induce demand and conseuqently vehicle travel. Further, consumer-focused retail practices with lucrative offers such as expedited shipping and free returns render frequent less-than-truckloads goods flow. Hence, while e-commerce has the potential to offer environmentally efficient means of goods distribution, changing consumer behavior and retailer practices puts sustianability of urban goods flow at risk.</p> <p>To conclude, what can you do the next time you have to shop? The direct comparison of in-store and online shopping showcase benefits of online shopping. Hence, you could try to replace your trips to store with online shopping. Further, you could try to consolidate your needs into a single purchase, enabling the e-retailer to make fewer vehicle trips to your house. With this I hope you can make an informed decision the next time you shop.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="moving-goods"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Should I visit a store or should I just check out Amazon? You might have asked yourself this question quite a few times by now. But have you ever considered the impacts of this decision on the environment Well, this article should help you make an informed decision next time.]]></summary></entry></feed>