<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://anmol1104.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://anmol1104.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-04-04T07:53:26+00:00</updated><id>https://anmol1104.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">LogNiti Lab</title><subtitle>Academic Profile </subtitle><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="https://anmol1104.github.io/blog/2024/2019-08-10-shinkansen/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title=""/><published>2024-04-04T07:53:26+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-04T07:53:26+00:00</updated><id>https://anmol1104.github.io/blog/2024/2019-08-10-shinkansen</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anmol1104.github.io/blog/2024/2019-08-10-shinkansen/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Shinkansen – The pride of Japan and the symbol of Japanese post-war recovery. But how does the High Speed Rail impact local economy? A look into Kyushu Shinkansen..</strong></p> <p>On October 1st 1964, just two weeks before the Tokyo Olympics, the first ever Shinkansen departed from Tokyo to Osaka, operating at speeds of 220 kmph and cutting down time by almost half, to 3 hrs and 45 mins. Due to its continuous success and improvements, today, a business executive from Tokyo can reach Osaka in just 2 hrs and 20 mins, which in a couple of decades is expected to go down to 67 mins with the opening of Chuo Shinkansen – to be developed as the first MagLev Shinkansen. And while it may seem that the Shinkansen project is all about achieving high speed, on the contrary it was never so. In the years post world war, the economic boom in Japan brought more and more people to its cities, and therefore in an effort to de-congest cities, both in terms of people and economic activity, the Japanese government took the initiative of building the first ever High Speed Rail* line from Tokyo to Osaka, known as the Tokaido Shinkansen. But did Shinkansen stand on its expectations?</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/3-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/3-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/3-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>While it can be argued, as with the chicken and egg problem, whether the rail (and in general the transportation infrastructure) follows the growth or does the growth follow the rail, however the literature has well established the impacts the transportation infrastructure can create in stimulating the economy. In particular for HSR, the reduction in travel time can have short term impacts in form of reduced commute, thereby affecting industrial productivity, while the long run impacts manifest in form of increased labor market and consequently increased market competition, thereby affecting the overall economic productivity. These impacts can also be studied at macro level in terms of output and productivity, meso level impacts in form of labor market changes, and micro impacts in form of land-use changes.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/4-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/4-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/4-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/4.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>To establish the economic impacts of Shinkansen, Hiramatsu studied Kyushu Shinkansen built on the Kyushu island (bottom left in the the first figure) connecting Fukuoka to Kagoshima via Kumamoto, and an upcoming line on the same island connecting Fukuoka with Nagasaki via Saga (see the figure above). While Fukuoka is the center of economic activity in the island, Kagoshima and Nagasaki also have relatively large economic scales. The economic impacts were studied in terms of change in population, jobs and production value – at a micro level for each prefecture, at meso level for the Kyushu island, and at the macro level for Japan. To have a comprehensive understanding of the economic impacts, Hiramatsu studied two scenarios – one with the currently present Fukuoka-Kagoshima route, and the other, along with the upcoming Fukuoka-Nagasaki route. The above mentioned economic impacts were realized using multi-regional Computational General Equilibrium (CGE), which is essentially a model that predicts the behavior of the economy subject to changes in economic structure or policy.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/5-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/5-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/5-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/5.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p><span style="font-size:0.5em;">Percentage change in population, jobs and production value proportional to the intensity of the color. The darker the color the higher is the percentage change due to the Shinkansen line. Note, lines are only made for illustration purpose, they do not truly represent true path of the line.</span></p> <p>The figure above presents the micro level impacts, i.e. percentage change in population, jobs and production value for the prefectures on Kyushu island, due to Fukuoka-Kagoshima and Fukuoka-Nagasaki Shinkansen lines. From the figures above, it is quite evident that prefectures that directly serve Shinkansen observe increment in population, indicating agglomeration instead of de-congestion. As for the jobs and production value, both increased in prefectures having Shinkansen connection, thus indicating a possibility of widening the economic disparity between the regions. For the entire Kyushu island though, an increase 0.46% in production value was observed, while for Japan, this value amounted to 0.07%. Note, this just from two Shinkansen lines on one of the islands of Japan. Scaling up for a total of 7 Shinkansen lines throughout Japan can have significant impacts on economy of Japan.</p> <p>As a conclusion, while the transportation infrastructure has the potential to de-congest cities and bring down economic disparity between regions, it is equally possible for the situation to exacerbate, with further agglomeration of people and jobs at the economic hubs. Developing transportation corridors over wider geographic area reduces possibilities of agglomeration of economy, as was observed with development of Fukuoka-Nagasaki line along with Fukuoka-Kagoshima line, benefiting Nagasaki and Saga prefectures (NW prefectures on Kyushu island), which earlier were disadvantaged with only Fukuoka-Kagoshima line operating on the island. And while completely eliminating economic disparity is impossible, equitable development of transportation infrastructure, connecting economic hubs with tier-2 or tier-3 cities and tourist destinations can bring about larger benefits in the region.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">What is the environmental costs of expedited shipping?</title><link href="https://anmol1104.github.io/blog/2020/expeditedshipping/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is the environmental costs of expedited shipping?"/><published>2020-02-05T13:23:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-05T13:23:00+00:00</updated><id>https://anmol1104.github.io/blog/2020/expeditedshipping</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anmol1104.github.io/blog/2020/expeditedshipping/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Get it delivered in 3 days, by tomorrow!, today!! We have often given into this instant gratification, though for a premium, but what is the real cost of expedited deliveries?</strong></p> <p>This blog is in continuation to an earlier blog –<a href="https://anmol1104.github.io/blog/2019/onlineshopping/"> Is online shopping environment friendly? </a>If you haven’t already checked that out, I would recommend you pause here, read the earlier blog and come back to enjoy this one.</p> <p>In the early days of online shopping, I remember getting packages delivered to my home in about a week or two from the day of purchase. In logistics jargon, this is called lead-time. During those days, my online purchases would pertain to things I knew I couldn’t get anywhere near me, such as PlayStation game disc maybe. But sometime during the last 7 years, my online cart has gradually transformed from having things I knew I cannot get anywhere near me, to things I know are easily available around, but I would rather save the time and effort of the travel. This bolsters the idea that travel is a derived demand, i.e. we travel not for the sake of it but for some other purpose, and hence if we can get that bag of groceries delivered to our door step, then we might as well. Coming back to lead-time, this change in shopping cart, from maybe not so essential to more essential and daily-use items has induced a need to get things as early as possible, thus reducing the lead-time available. This surely has affected the way supply-chains organize and consolidate themselves, but what are the impacts on the end-user (and the community in general) beyond the premium you paid for the expedited delivery?</p> <p>Before we look into the numbers, lets first understand what happens when temporal constraints become stricter. Generally speaking, the more time available at the e-retailer’s disposal, the better can the delivery tours be planned, i.e. the e-retailer can consolidate as much demand as possible and thus better utilize the capacity of the delivery vehicle. And hence it is argued that since e-retailers consolidate the demand, and optimize the routes, e-commerce can reduce shopping travel related negative externalities. However, any such benefits were wiped out by rush deliveries as it compels the e-retailers to ship packages at lower consolidation levels. Thus, it can be argued that temporal constraints compel the e-retailers to plan higher amounts of shorter tours which essentially increases the distances driven, thereby increasing costs and emissions.</p> <p>In particular, the number of deliveries made in a tour could go down from 300 to 10 – a reduction of 97%. Further, vehicle miles traveled (VMT) per package, often used to understand impacts on congestion, could go up from 0.2 mi to 1.4 mi, about 7 times as much. Consequently, urban goods distritbution could witness substantial increase in externalities such as greenhouse gas and criteria pollutant emissions. Moreover, in monetary terms, the cost of distribution for the e-retailer could go up from $1.8 to $7.2, which could either be transferred onto the customer as a premium for faster delivery, or could be subsidized to gain larger market shares. However, beyond the premium, the increased emissions and congestion results in an externality cost to the society, which could go up from $0.1 per package to $0.7 per package, a hike of about 7 times.</p> <p>To conclude, it can be argued that last-mile deliveries are logistically efficient and can produce savings in cost and externalities in comparison to shopping in-store. However, the recent trends in last-mile delivery, such as expedited and time-window based deliveries, especially observed in the e-grocery and food delivery segment of e-commerce, seem to be environmentally unsustainable. Yet, more and more firms today offer such lucrative offers in order to capture larger market shares, and generate larger revenue and profit. Although not discussed here, free returns is yet another way in which e-retailers pursue larger market share. The tendency to return a product is not founded in the functional error of the product but can be ascribed to lack of information about the fit and suitability of a product. The apparel segment especially observes high rate of return, which can go as high as 45%, i.e. almost every other product is returned. And although reverse logistics incur additional operational cost (also emissions) to the e-retailer, not providing free return puts the retailer at the risk of losing the customer. This compels the e-retailer to provide free return, face the additional operational cost, produce more emissions just to keep the consumer happy. Hence, in general, one can conclude that the environmental efficiency of deliveries reduces significantly as companies make such lucrative offers to its consumers. The above results and discussion therefore highlights the importance of stakeholders, in particular, for consumers in consolidating their demand, for e-retailers in consolidating the deliveries, and for planners and regulators in managing the urban freight system to foster sustainability.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="moving-goods"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Get it delivered in 3 days, by tomorrow!, today!! We have often given into this instant gratification, though for a premium, but what is the real cost of expedited deliveries?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Uber vs. car, taxi, or transit?</title><link href="https://anmol1104.github.io/blog/2019/uber/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Uber vs. car, taxi, or transit?"/><published>2019-08-18T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-18T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://anmol1104.github.io/blog/2019/uber</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anmol1104.github.io/blog/2019/uber/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>There is demand, there is supply, and then there is Uber, connecting the two like never before. While on one hand, Uber provides accessible and affordable mobility, its influence on individual’s decision making has potential consequences on car ownership, driver jobs and transit ridership. Lets dive into each one of them in this blog.</strong></p> <p>The last couple of decades has witnessed a radical change in the transportation sector, be it for moving the people or moving goods. With e-commerce transforming our shopping experience and ride-hailing services, also known as Transportation Network Company (TNC), influencing our commute, the on-demand economy has become an integral part of our lives today. In the US alone, the TNC ridership amounted for 4.2 billion trips in 2018, a growth of ~62% from 2017. This increasing shift towards an on-demand mobility service competes with car, traditional taxis and transit in terms of car ownership, driver jobs and transit ridership. Before we understand what these impacts are, lets take a look at who are the adapters of the on-demand economy and who is most influenced by it.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>The above two figures present user demographics and user adaption rates for the two on-demand services – ride-hailing and e-commerce. As an example, the first figure tells us that 52% of the people who used ride-hailing service were males, while the second figure tells us that 9% of the males used the ride-hailing service. An important point to note here is that despite of the obvious convenience of on-demand services, the elderly population, for whom it is touted to be the most useful, least uses it, potentially due to lack of experience with smart phones and on-demand economy. However, the key takeaway from the above two figures is the striking similarity of the highs and the lows of user demographics and adaption for ride-hailing and online shopping. Thus the market for the two on-demand services is similar, i.e. those who tend to shop on Amazon also tend to use Uber. And although, ride-hailing and online shopping both together will influence individual’s decision making, in this blog we only look at the impacts from ride-hailing service on car ownership, taxi-driver jobs and transit ridership.</p> <p><strong>vs. Car</strong></p> <p>For most people buying a car is the highest investment they make after buying a house. But with the advent of on-demand taxi services like Uber, not owning a car might as well be a smart decision. With that being said, in a study performed at UC Davis, on an aggregate the authors did not find any significant reduction in vehicle ownership for ride-hailing users. However, there was considerable heterogeneity within this information, and the study found that the more frequent users of ride-hailing service did indeed have a lower vehicle ownership compared to less frequent users. The study found similar results for self-reported change in personal vehicle usage (in terms of vehicle miles driven), i.e. more frequent users of ride-hailing service drove less with their personal cars. Thus the opportunity cost from an idle sitting car gives more reasons to dispose off or rent out the asset.</p> <p><strong>vs. Taxi</strong></p> <p>The conventional taxi service sector is a highly regulated one in the US, limiting number of taxis and fare in the city. However, Uber, for as much as it may seem like, is not considered as a taxi-company, primarily because Uber is just a platform that connects customer demand for travel with driver supply. And hence it can easily flout the taxi regulations. Thus the entry of Uber in the field renders similar impacts as if the taxi-service sector was de-regulated. In particular, Berger et al. study the impacts of Uber entry on taxi driver jobs and compare the effects with 1978 Airline Deregulation Act and Motor Carrier Act 1980. As with the previous two deregulation acts, this study also found a decrease in driver wages by about 10% due to Uber entry, however, the total taxi driver supply remained unaffected. Specifically , the wage-employed drivers are worse affected compared to the self-employed drivers, who could switch once Uber entered the market.</p> <p><strong>vs. Transit</strong></p> <p>While above we looked at the interplay of Uber with Car and Taxi, with transit however, the interplay is unique. Uber provides obvious benefits with its reliability, convenience and accessibility. With that being said, transit can be cheaper, especially for daily commute purpose. And hence, Uber can be an alternate mode to transit – thus substituting for it, or can even complement transit for the first and last-mile of the travel. This interplay is sensitive to individual’s behavior in terms of value for time, money, convenience and safety. It is easy to think of Uber as a substitute to transit, however, if Uber cannot produce significant time savings compared to transit such that it outdoes its additional cost, Uber is very likely to be a complement to transit. Largely, the literature has found strong correlation between transit use and Uber use, however no causal inference has been deduced yet. In particular, a study conducted in the US found transit usage to be positively affected by Uber entry, increasing ridership by as much as 5% especially for transit systems in bigger cities, however with some significant difference in this effect for rail based and bus based transit systems. Yet there are certain studies who have reported substitution effect as users of ride-hailing service reported the next best alternative to be public transit.</p> <p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p> <p>Whether one likes Uber or not, it is likely to dominate the market for long. While it can have potential benefits by reducing vehicle ownership and complementing for transit, it has had disruptive impacts on taxi-service sector. And it is important to note, that even if car ownership does go down and if indeed Uber does complement transit, it can induce demand leading to worsening of traffic related externalities like congestion and pollution. Understanding the impacts of Uber is hence essential for policy makers so that cities can implement policies that can minimize the disruptive impacts without inhibiting individual mobility.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="moving-people"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There is demand, there is supply, and then there is Uber, connecting the two like never before. While on one hand, Uber provides accessible and affordable mobility, its influence on individual’s decision making has potential consequences on car ownership, driver jobs and transit ridership. Lets dive into each one of them in this blog.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is online shopping environment friendly?</title><link href="https://anmol1104.github.io/blog/2019/onlineshopping/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is online shopping environment friendly?"/><published>2019-08-02T16:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-02T16:03:00+00:00</updated><id>https://anmol1104.github.io/blog/2019/onlineshopping</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anmol1104.github.io/blog/2019/onlineshopping/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Should I visit a store or should I just check out Amazon? You might have asked yourself this question quite a few times by now. But have you ever considered the impacts of this decision on the environment? Well, this article should help you make an informed decision next time.</strong></p> <p>August 11, 1994 marks the day when the first ever online transaction was made, and since then, the internet has continuously reshaped the way we shop. E-commerce, a term completely unknown to us a couple of decades ago, has gradually become a fundamental part of our daily lives.</p> <p>With the increasing influence of internet on our decisions as to what and when to shop, how and how much to shop, the underlying question posed onto us is whether online shopping is good for us? i.e. whether online shopping is substituting (replacing) or complementing (co-existing with) in-store shopping? The literature on this largely weighs towards the complementary behavior, thus arguing for an increased travel activity, one from the delivery vans serving the online retail demand, and the other from the personal trips to stores. Yet another aspect of online shopping is the induced demand – an increase in number of purchases made by a consumer, be it online or in-store. Remember this, because it will come to bite us later.</p> <p>To answer the question posed above, I modeled the shopping choice – whether to shop online, to shop in-store, or to not shop at all, with socioeconomic parameters of the individual (such as age, income, education level etc.), city related parameters and some other temporal parameters. The resulting model tells us which factors influence one’s choice to shop online or in-store, or not shop at all. This dis-aggregate model was then applied over the synthetically generated population of the city of San Francisco (SF) to determine people who shop in-store and/or online. The resulting externalities, i.e. traffic in terms of vehicle miles traveled (VMT), and pollution in terms of greenhouse gas emissions (CO and CO2), as well as criteria pollutant emissions (NOx and PM) were estimated from the shopping related travel.</p> <p>First, I present here one-to-one direct comparison of externalities from in-store and online shopping in terms of equivalence of one with the other, i.e. how many online purchases produce the same amount of externalities as the in-store purchase. Turns out, around 8 online purchases produce as much vehicle travel as 1 in-store purchase, thus reducing the traffic. Consequently, if everyone was to only shop online, significant reduction in emissions can be produced, barring NOx emissions. Note, delivery trucks are heavy emitters of criteria pollutant emissions, especially NOx emissions.</p> <pre><code class="language-echarts">{
  "title": {
    "text": "Comparison of in-store and online shopping"
  },
  "responsive": true,
  "tooltip": {},
  "xAxis": {
    "data": ["VMT", "CO", "CO2", "PM", "NOx"]
  },
  "yAxis": {},
  "series": [
    {
      "name": "ratio of in-store to online",
      "type": "bar",
      "data": [8.1, 7.8, 2.7, 1.8, 0.8]
    }
  ]
}
</code></pre> <p><br/> Having established a direct one-to-one comparison, I then estimated the impact of online shopping accounting for the consumer behavior through the shopping choice model. Note, the current omni-channel retail scenario implies that some people shop in-store while others shop online. The results showcase a 7% reduction in overall VMT due to online purchases. Consequently, the urban environment witnesses a significant reduction in emissions, barring of course the NOx emissions.</p> <pre><code class="language-echarts">{
  "title": {
    "text": "Impact of online shopping"
  },
  "responsive": true,
  "tooltip": {},
  "xAxis": {
    "data": ["VMT", "CO", "CO2", "PM", "NOx"]
  },
  "yAxis": {},
  "series": [
    {
      "name": "percentage change",
      "type": "bar",
      "data": [7.0, 7.0, 4.9, 3.4, -1.8]
    }
  ]
}
</code></pre> <p><br/> These results therefore pose the question, why push for cleaner freight movement? Well, because these results are founded on current consumer behavior and retailer practices. It is important to consider the potential impact on consumer behavior as e-commerce can induce demand and conseuqently vehicle travel. Further, consumer-focused retail practices with lucrative offers such as expedited shipping and free returns render frequent less-than-truckloads goods flow. Hence, while e-commerce has the potential to offer environmentally efficient means of goods distribution, changing consumer behavior and retailer practices puts sustianability of urban goods flow at risk.</p> <p>To conclude, what can you do the next time you have to shop? The direct comparison of in-store and online shopping showcase benefits of online shopping. Hence, you could try to replace your trips to store with online shopping. Further, you could try to consolidate your needs into a single purchase, enabling the e-retailer to make fewer vehicle trips to your house. With this I hope you can make an informed decision the next time you shop.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="moving-goods"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Should I visit a store or should I just check out Amazon? You might have asked yourself this question quite a few times by now. But have you ever considered the impacts of this decision on the environment Well, this article should help you make an informed decision next time.]]></summary></entry></feed>